A Guide to the Ernest M. Dickerman Papers, 1936-2005: SC 0143
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Ernest M. Dickerman Papers,
1936-2005
Special Collections, James Madison University
Ernest M. Dickerman, 1910-1998
SC 0143
5.07 cubic feet; 4 boxes, 1 rolled storage container, 1 flat file
The Ernest M. Dickerman Papers, 1936-2005, contain a wide variety of materials that document Dickerman's efforts to obtain Congressional designations of wilderness for various tracts of public land, primarily in Virginia. The collection also contains papers of the Virginia Wilderness Committee (VWC), a grass roots conservation group that Dickerman led.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Ernest M. Dickerman in November 1994. After Dickerman's death in 1998, several additions of papers were donated by his nephew and executor, Robert Dickerman.
Bio/Historical Note
Ernest M. Dickerman was born December 22, 1910 in Austin, Illinois, and moved to the Adirondacks in New York at three years old. When he was about six years old, the family moved to Richmond, Virginia where his mother died of tuberculosis when Dickerman was nine. Sometime later, the family moved to Roanoke. Dickerman attended Gettysburg Academy and Oberlin College (class of 1931). In 1934 he began working for the newly created Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA) in Knoxville, Tennessee. Immediately, he fell in love with the Great Smoky Mountains, met conservationist Harvey Broome, and became deeply involved in the battles to preserve the Great Smoky Mountains National Park from development. He was a 1936 charter member of The Wilderness Society and knew many of the greatest conservationists of the day, including Bob Marshall, Sigurd Olson, Olaus Murie, and Howard Zahniser.
After a few years at TVA, Dickerman took a job with a plastics molding firm (apparently called the Patent Button Co. of Tennessee), also in Knoxville. He retired from a position as production manager in 1966, and in 1969 moved to the headquarters office of The Wilderness Society in Washington, D.C. as a staff organizer. He traveled frequently to teach citizens how to identify, map, and build support for wilderness areas throughout the East and Midwest. He also lobbied Congress on numerous wilderness bills, wrestled with federal land managing agencies (Forest Service, National Park Service, Fish & Wildlife Service), and was highly instrumental in passage of the 1975 Eastern Wilderness Bill. During the 1960s Dickerman also served as manager for the Robert Marshall Wilderness Fund, as evidenced by a notebook of typed minutes from the first thirteen years of the Fund (established by the will of Robert Marshall), 1940-1953, in which are inserted several 1968 letters to and from Dickerman.
When he retired from The Wilderness Society in 1976 and moved to his nephew's newly acquired mountain farm near Buffalo Gap in Swoope, Augusta County, Virginia, he was almost immediately elected president of the Virginia Wilderness Committee. At that time he inherited the organization's files prior to 1976. The Virginia Wilderness Committee (VWC) had been founded in Williamsburg at William & Mary College by a small group of private citizens in 1969 to promote the federal designation of wilderness in Virginia according to the 1964 Wilderness Act. The VWC also became involved in various other issues relevant to preservation of the natural landscape. VWC volunteers donate issues of the newsletter and occasional other VWC documents to keep these current in Dickerman's papers.
Although he held an official position in the VWC only until 1979, Dickerman was the guiding spirit in the movement for Virginia wilderness both before and long after those dates. He was widely renowned for his combination of optimism and canny strategizing, his politeness in dealing with adversaries, and his sense of humor. He died on July 31, 1998. In 1999, friends and colleagues produced a book of tributes titled Ernie Dickerman, 1910-1998: A Tribute.
Scope and Content
The Ernest M. Dickerman Papers, 1936-2005, contain a wide variety of materials that document Dickerman's efforts to obtain Congressional designations of wilderness for various tracts of public land, primarily in Virginia. The collection also contains papers of the Virginia Wilderness Committee (VWC), a grass roots conservation group that Dickerman led. These papers include correspondence, maps, field notes, reports, news clippings, wilderness proposals, minutes, financial statements, newsletters and other materials, 1940 - current, with most materials dating 1962-1999. The collection documents Dickerman's activities as a leader of the movement to designate wilderness areas on public lands in the eastern United States under the Wilderness Act of 1964 and the Eastern Wilderness Act of 1975. Operating papers of the Virginia Wilderness Committee, a grass roots conservation group of which Dickerman served as president for several years, are also included.
Series 1: Places and Policies, 1962-2001, contains maps, reports, conference agendas, environmental assessments, congressional testimony, and some correspondence dealing with specific places, topical issues, and policies of public land agencies. The Laurel Fork, Virginia folders hold the largest body of materials; Laurel Fork was Dickerman's favorite place in Virginia, and he worked intensively (and successfully) against a proposed gas line through it.
Series 2: Correspopndence and Personal Files, 1940-1999, includes carbon copies of Dickerman's outgoing letters, original incoming letters, notebooks, texts for speeches, data sheets he composed about various issues, and other items. One folder contains personal Christmas messages, biographical articles, obituaries, and remembrances.
Series 3: Virginia Wilderness Committee, 1969-2005, includes operational documents including minutes, financial reports, newsletters, Virginia Wilderness coalition notes, the 1984 Virginia Wilderness Bill, and wilderness proposals.
Series 4: Maps, 1936-1991, contains 25 maps described at an item level in the container list.
Organization
This collection is arranged in five series:
Series 1: Places and Policies, 1962-2001
Series 2: Correspondence and Personal Files, 1940-1999
Series 3: Virginia Wilderness Committee (VWC), 1969-2005
Series 4: Maps, 1936-1991
Related Material
Wilderness Society Records, CoONS130, Conservation Collection, The Denver Pubilc Library.
Ernie Dickerman, interviewed by Dominic Pisciotta, 1994, Sd-Arch 6-3, Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University, Harrisonburg, VA.
Separated Material
A duplicate copy of Elizabeth Murray's, ed. Ernie Dickerman, 1910-1998: A Tribute (The Wilderness Society, 1999) was removed from the collection and added to the Special Collections rare book holdings. A copy is also retained in the collection.
Bibliography
"Grandad of the Eastern Wilderness," Sierra Magazine, Nov/Dec, 1986.
Bolgiano, Chris. The Appalachian Forest, A Search for Roots and Renewal. Mechanicsburg, PA: Stackpole Books, 1998.
Murray, Elizabeth, ed. Ernie Dickerman, 1910-1998: A Tribute. The Wilderness Society, 1999.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Dickerman, Ernest M., 1910-1998; Dickerman, Ernest M., 1910-1998 -- Correspondence; United States. Forest Service -- History; Virginia Wilderness Committee; United States. Wilderness Act; United States. Wilderness Act of 1984; United States. Wilderness Act of 1988; United States. Eastern Wilderness Areas Act of 1975; Sierra Club. Virginia Chapter; Wilderness Society; Wilderness areas -- Virginia -- Management; Wilderness areas -- Law and legislation; Environmental protection -- Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- Citizen participation; National parks and reserves -- United States -- Southern Region; National parks and reserves -- United States -- Virginia; Forest reserves -- Multiple use; Forest reserves -- Recreational use; Forest management; Wildlife management; Wildlife refuges -- United States -- Southern Region; Forest policy -- United States -- History; Forests and forestry -- History; Lobbying -- Law and legislation; Lobbyists -- United States; Wildlife conservationists -- Virginia; Saint Mary's Wilderness (Va.); James River Face Wilderness Area (Va.); Ramsey's Draft Wilderness (Va.); Mountain Lake Wilderness Area (Va.); Peters Mountain Wilderness Area (Va.); Rich Hole Roadless Area (Va.); George Washington National Forest (Va. and W. Va.); Jefferson National Forest
- Series 1: Places and Policies, 1962-2001
  - Alaska-Pipeline, etc., 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Assateague, 1970-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Assorted State Issues, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Back Creek-Pumped Storage Project, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Back Bay-Vehicular Access Flight, 1970-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Back Bay-Wilderness Proposals, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Big Levels/St. Marys, 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bull Run Mountain, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Central Atlantic Environment Center, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conservation Council of Virginia, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Crawford Mountain, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cumberland Gap, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dismal Swamp, 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Eastern Wilderness Bill-House, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Eastern Wilderness Bill-Senate, 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Eastern Wilderness Bill-Senate Hearings, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Eastern Wilderness Bill-Wilderness Areas, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 16A)
  - Eastern Wilderness Bill-Citizens For Eastern Wilderness Memoranda, 1973-1975 (Box 1, Folder 16B)
  - Gathright, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hipes Dam, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - James River Face, Cave Mtn. Lake, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Laurel Fork, 1962-1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Laurel Fork-Gas Line Proposal, 1975-1995 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Laurel Fork-Gas Line Proposal, 1975-1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Laurel Fork-Environmental Assessment, Decision Notice and Responses, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Little River, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Little Stoney, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Mason Neck, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Massanutten, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mt. Pleasant, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Mt. Rogers, 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mountain Lake, Peters Mountain, Mill Creek, 1974, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National Forests, 1969-1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - National Forests-Unit Planning, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ramseys Draft, 1968-1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Rich Hole, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Roadless Areas, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Roadless Areas, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Salem Church Dam, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Shenandoah National Park Wilderness, 1967-1973 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Shenandoah Wilderness, 1987-2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Sierra Club - Virginia Groups, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Environmental Cooridination Legislation, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Virginia State Parks, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Wetlands, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Wild Areas Bill, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Series 2: Correspondence and Personal Files, 1940-1999
  - Correspondence, 1962-1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1977 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, January-June 1978 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, July-December 1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, January-April 1979 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, May-August 1979 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Correspondence, September-December 1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Master List of Basic Statements on Wilderness, 1983-1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Personal: obituaries, biography, Christmas cards, and photographs, 1967-1999 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Talks by Ernest M. Dickerman, 1979-1996 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Great Smoky Mountains National Park, 1965-1967 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Tennessee Citizens for Wilderness Planning, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Wilderness Workshops, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Dickerman's notebooks, 1966-1976 (Box 3, Folder 15A)
  - Robert Marshall Wilderness Fund Minutes Book, 1940-1969 (Box 3, Folder 15B)
- Series 3: Virginia Wilderness Committee (VWC), 1969-2005
  - Virginia Wilderness Bill Hearings, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Wilderness Coalition, 1979-1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - VWC Correspondence, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - VWC Finances, 1969-2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - VWC Hot Line, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - VWC Minutes Membership, 1971-1979 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - VWC Minutes Membership, 1980-1997 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - VWC Newsletters, 1970-2005 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Wilderness Proposals (folder 1 of 2), 1970s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Wilderness Proposals (folder 2 of 2), 1970s (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Wilderness Proposals, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Wilderness Proposals (folder 1 of 2), 1990s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Wilderness Proposals (folder 2 of 2), 1990s (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series 4: Maps, 1936-1991
  - Maps 1-5, 7-9, 15-24, 1936-1991, undated (Mapcase 1, Drawer 3, Folder 1)
    - Map 1: Thornwood Gas, Inc.; Pipeline Gathering Route Location Map; Pocahontas, Pendleton and Randolph Counties, West Virginia; Scale 1=2000, undated
    - Map 2: US Department of Agriculture, Forest Service; George Washington National Forest; Virginia and West Virginia, 1936
    - Map 3: United States, Department of the Interior, Geological Survey; Great Smoky Mountains National Park and Vicinity; Tennessee and North Carolina, Scale 1:125000, 1949
      Scope and Content
      With lines probably indicating proposed wilderness.
    - Map 4: Proposed Southern Nantahala Wilderness Area; Hightower Bald G.A.-N.C. and Dillard G.A.-N.C., 1946
    - Map 5: United States, Department of the Interior, Geological Survey; Tennessee Valley Authority, Maps and Surveys Branch; Shooting Creek Quadrangle 159-SW, Rainbow Springs Quadrangle 159-SE, Prentiss Quadrangle 167-SW, North Carolina, 7.5 Minute Series (Topographic), undated
    - Map 7: United States, Department of the Interior, Geological Survey; Thornwood Quadrangle, Snow Mountain Quadrangle, WVA-VA, 1969
    - Map 8: United States, Department of the Interior, Geological Survey; Commonwealth of Virginia; Snowden Quadrangle, 1966
    - Map 9a-9b: Proposed Whitetop Mountain Wilderness Area and Addition to the Lewis Fork Wilderness Area, Scale 1 = 2000. 9b, undated
      Overlay with proposed wilderness boundaries.
    - Map 15: Proposed Chattachoochee Wilderness Area, United States, Department of the Interior, Geological Survey; Jacks Gap Quadrangle, Tray Mountain Quadrangle, Georgia, 1950, 1957
    - Map 16: United States Geological Survey; Shenandoah National Park (Central Section), 1969
    - Map 17: United States Geological Survey; Shenandoah National Park (Southern Section), 1969
    - Map 18: United States Geological Survey; Shenandoah National Park (Northern Section), 1969
    - Map 19: Three Ridges Proposed Wilderness Area, United States Geological Survey Quadrangles: Big Levels, Sherando, Massies Mill, Horseshoe Mountain, Citizen Proposal compiled by James Madison University Geography Department, December 1990
    - Map 20: Mount Pleasant Proposed Wilderness Area, United States Geological Survey Quadrangles: Forks of Buffalo, Montebello, Citizen Proposal compiled by James Madison University Geography Department, February 1991
    - Map 21: Kelley Mountain-Big Levels Proposed Wilderness Area, United States Geological Survey Quadrangles: Big Levels, Sherando, Citizen Proposal compiled by James Madison University Geography Department, February 1991
    - Map 22: Skidmore Fork Proposed Wilderness Area, United States Geological Survey Quadrangles: Brandywine, February 1991
    - Map 23: The Priest Proposed Wilderness Area, United States Geological Survey Quadrangles: Massies Mill, May 1991
    - Map 24: Ramsey's Draft Addition Proposed Wilderness Area, United States Geological Survey Quadrangles: Palo Alto, West Augusta, McDowell, December 1990
  - Maps 6, 10-14, 25, 1965-1984 (Storage 1)
    - Map 6: James River Face Wilderness and Vicinity, March 1976
    - Map 10: Beartown, Roadless and Undeveloped Area, Jefferson N.F. VA., 9/15/77, Hutchinson Rock and Tazwell South Quads, Scale 1:24000, 1977
      With attached information.
    - Map 11: Mountain Lake Wilderness Study Area, Virginia, Jefferson N.F., Scale 1:24000, 1965
    - Map 12: Little Wilson and Thunder Ridge Roadless and Undeveloped Areas, Jefferson N.F. VA., 9/15/77, Trout Dale Quad, Scale 1:24000, 1977
    - Map 13: Devils Fork and Roaring Branch Roadless and Undeveloped Areas, Jefferson N.F. VA., 9/15/77, East Stone Gap Quad, Scale 1:24000; Roaring Branch, Roadless and Undeveloped Area, Jefferson N.F. VA., 9/15/77, Appalachia & Big Stone Gap Quads, Scale 1:24000, 1977
    - Map 14: Little Dry Run and Lewis Fork Roadless and Undeveloped Areas, Jefferson N.F. VA., 9/15/77, Speedwell, VA Quad, Scale 1:24000; Lewis Fork, Roadless and Undeveloped Area, Jefferson N.F. VA., 9/15/77, Whitetop Mtn. Quad, Scale 1:24000, 1977
    - Map 25: Rough Mountain and Rich Hole, George Washington N. F. Va., 1/25/1984, Scale 1:24000, 1984